{
  "version": 2.0,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "1. Chromatography is defined as a biophysical technique employed for the separation, identification and purification of the individual components of a mixture, based on their differential properties, for qualitative and quantitative analysis. It can be used to separate a mixture of _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Gases",
        "b": "Oil and water ",
        "c": "Different cereals",
        "d": "Both a and b"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
   
    {
      "question": "2. The chromatographic technique that exploits the property of highly specific binding between an immobilized ligand and a only single component of the analyte mixture, is termed as _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Affinity Chromatography",
        "b": "SEC",
        "c": "TLC",
        "d": "Ion-Exchange Chromatography"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Affinity chromatography can be used to purify biomolecules using corresponding resins to which they specifically bind. Find the correct match of the resin and its eluate",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Carbohydrate resin – Biotinylated biomolecules ",
        "b": "Glutathione resin – protein with hexa-histidine tag",
        "c": "Ni NTA resin - protein with GST tag",
        "d": "Protein A/protein G resin – Immunoglobulin"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Affinity chromatography is used to isolate biomolecules bound to one another and study their interaction using a ligand that specifically binds to one of the biomolecules in the complex. This technique is termed as _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "SEC",
        "b": "IMAC",
        "c": "Pull-down assay",
        "d": "None of the above"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. To elute the desired analyte, it needs to be freed from the analyte-ligand complex. This is achieved by adding in a competitor that binds more strongly with the ligand. This method is called specific elution. Non-specific elution is achieved using _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "pH change",
        "b": "Solvent change ",
        "c": "Reversibly denaturing the analyte protein",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. In immobilized metal affinity chromatography (IMAC), the commonly used metal is _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Ni",
        "b": "Mg",
        "c": "Co",
        "d": "Both a and b"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Ni-NTA chromatography is a common type of IMAC commonly used in FPLC for the purification of proteins with a recombinant hexahistidine tag. What is the principle behind the affinity?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "NTA is a tetradentate ligand that coordinates Ni2+ to which imidazole group of His binds",
        "b": "NTA is a hexadentate ligand that coordinates Ni2+ to which imidazole group of His binds",
        "c": "NTA has a strong affinity for imidazole group of His",
        "d": "NTA helps to bind His strongly to the Sepharose"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. FPLC is a type of affinity chromatographic technique that uses Ni-NTA IMAC for the purification of proteins. FPLC stands for _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Fluid Pressure liquid chromatography",
        "b": "Fast Pressure liquid chromatography",
        "c": "Fast Protein liquid chromatography",
        "d": "Both b and c"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. In FPLC, the flow rate of the liquid mobile phase through the column can be controlled",
      "answers": {
        "a": "True",
        "b": "False"
       
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. FPLC finds application in _______.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Purification and analysis of proteins",
        "b": "RNA isolation and plasmid DNA purification",
        "c": "Purification of synthetic oligonucleotides",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
     
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }
  ]
}
